Quiescent endothelial cells upregulate
fatty acid beta oxidation for vascular
protection via redux homeostasis. Well,
well,
don't mind if I do. Unless you're a
mannequin, you have arteries that allow
blood containing oxygen, nutrients, and
so much more across your entire body.
And you better believe it, those
arteries are very much alive in their
own right. If they're not healthy, you
typically have increased risk of stroke,
plaque buildup in your arteries and just
an overall increased mortality risk. So
why and how do we fix it? The reason
comes down, at least in a major way, to
these cells that line your arteries
called endothelial cells. Endothelial
cells control the expansion and
shrinking of your arteries, reducing and
increasing blood pressure through the
release of molecules that interact with
nearby cells. and they do so much more.
For now, just know that healthy
endothelial cells are critical to good
health, especially in relation to
cardiovascular health. Unfortunately,
aging and general insults like smoking,
poor diet, lack of exercise, and so on
can lead to endothelial cell stress. And
one sign of that stress is
proliferation. Said differently, the
cells begin multiplying. That's a
problem because these cells, as you can
see from the images, are tightly packed
together and they create this barrier
which prevents things like immune cells
from invading into the subendothelial
regions and generally creating a
pro-inflammatory environment. In their
healthy functional state, endothelial
cells are in their quscent state, a
nonprololiferative state. In this
quscent state, they rely on fat for
their energy needs. And if they become
perturbed like with the loss of the
barrier integrity, they switch to a more
glycolytic or carbohydrate sugar
metabolism. In fact, we can see that
here. In this experiment, the
researchers assessed what metabolism the
endothelial cells were utilizing when in
a proliferative stage akin to stress in
this context and in a less proliferative
stage like in quiesence. You can see
there's a direct relationship between
the downward trend of proliferation in
line with a reduced glycolysis as well
as increased fatty acid oxidation. So
that's fat metabolism. You don't see it
yet, but that shift is extremely
important for one understanding the
health of your arteries and also two how
to convince these cells to stay in their
quscent state. In fact, that metabolic
switch from carbohydrate metabolism, the
glycolytic to the fatty acids. So fat
metabolism is also shown here in a
different crucial way as you'll soon
realize.
We're looking at two critical proteins
involved in carbohydrate metabolism. So
glycolysis as well as fat metabolism. So
we're looking at the amount of each
protein found in these endothelial cells
over six days as the cells transition
like we saw previously. In fact, here's
the previous data again. Notice that as
the fatty acid oxidation, so fat
metabolism increases, so does the CPT-1
protein indicated by darker splotches.
On the other hand, as CPT-1 increases,
PFKFB3
decreases. Why does any of that matter?
Well, it matters because CPT-1 is
located inside the outer mitochondrial
membrane. Yes, those organels that
produce cellular energy, the powerhouse
of the cell, as some might say, it is
responsible partly for allowing fat
molecules into the mitochondrian to be
metabolized for usable cellular energy.
So, it makes sense that the cells would
be producing more of it as fat
metabolism increases. On the other hand,
PFKFB is an enzyme that produces among
other things activating molecules for
glycolysis, the carbohydrate metabolism.
Specifically, it activates an enzyme
called phosphopructokinace
PFK. In doing so, it allows carbohydrate
or glucose metabolism to work. Again, it
makes sense that it might decrease based
on what we know. But while we understand
now that there's a relationship between
metabolism and its quessence or in the
negative scenario, increase stress and
proliferation. Why do the cells prefer
fat metabolism? Well, for that we have
to dive in deeper into the powerhouse of
the cell and look at what happens to
carbohydrates and fats when they undergo
metabolism. Because here is where we get
answers. Now that the researchers know
the proliferative or stressed
endothelial cells have more glucose
carbohydrate focus and the quscent
healthier cells are more fat focused.
They used labeled fat molecules to track
what happens to the fat molecules as
they enter the TCA cycle. Also known as
the KB cycle. Maybe you know it from
that one, that second one in your
biology classes. So here they're
measuring citrate levels, which is
produced at one of the earliest steps of
the TCA cycle as either glucose from
glycolysis or fat from beta oxidation.
So that's fat metabolism comes into the
TCA cycle. There's some uh details here
that I'm keeping out for brevity, but
this is in basic terms correct. So on
the left we have our proliferative
endothelial cells and on the right we
have our quscentin cells. As labeled fat
molecules attract, we can see the qosin
cells produce more citrate. That's going
to be more important soon. But at least
we can see that the cells that favor fat
utilize it more in their metabolism.
Similarly, when doing similar
experiments looking at glycolysis, there
is greater metabolism in the
proliferative cells. Okay, so we have
more citrate. Why does this matter?
Well, your cells when stressed can
generate a lot of damaging molecules
like reactive oxygen species. These
molecules are unstable and interact with
the cellular environment around them
causing damage to the surrounding area
in and out of the cell. So citrate plays
a role by being eventually converted to
isoccitrate which can then be used
indirectly to generate more NADPH.
NADPH is an extremely important molecule
in that it allows your cells internal
antioxidant systems so systems that
neutralize reactive oxygen species to
function. Essentially, it gets used by a
protein called glutathione reductase,
which recharges a potent cellular
antioxidant called glutathione, which
then interacts with and neutralizes the
aforementioned reactive oxygen species.
So, without citrate, way at the
beginning, you could have less
recharging potential for glutathione,
meaning that the cells are subject to
greater concentrations of these damaging
reactive oxygen species. In fact, if we
look at the gene expression of some of
the NADPH producing enzymes like
isoccitrate dehydrogenase here there are
two isoforms or versions of IDH that's
isocitrate dehydrogenase and we have our
two cells proliferative and quscent
again one isoform doesn't budge but the
second one does increase by about 40% in
quscent cells over the proliferative and
when we look further specifically ically
at the molecule that we want out of all
this. So, NADPH, we see that the
chosinin cells again have greater
amounts, a good thing here. But if you
look closer, these data actually tell us
something else too. Notice the CPT1
there at the bottom. That's a knockdown
experiment. Meaning that the researchers
have knocked down the gene expression in
a rudimentary explanation of the CPT1
protein that we talked about earlier. if
you knock it down. So there are low
levels of the protein that's indicated
by the plus symbols there. We clearly
see this increase in NADPH is eliminated
indicating that either CPT1 is directly
tied to NADPH or if we reduce fat
metabolism artificially by stopping fat
molecules from entering the
mitochondrian, NADPH is affected, which
makes sense considering that we might be
reducing citrate. But let's take it a
step further. Here we have the exact
same conditions except we're only
looking at the healthy quscent cells and
we're measuring the reactive oxygen
species. So the higher the bar the
worse. Again if we have a knockdown of
CPT1 there's an effect. We see an
increase in reactive oxygen species and
we add a dose of these oxidizing
molecules to the cells. The cells are
less able to keep them down overall.
This again implicates fat metabolism is
likely helping these cells fight
damaging molecules. All right, fair
enough. But exactly how does this
translate to arterial damage,
cardiovascular disease, and so on? Well,
for that the researchers measured PI1 or
plasmminogen activator inhibitor 1,
which is a protein that inhibits the
destruction of clots in the arteries. So
typically the greater concentration of P
AI1 in the blood the greater the risk of
clots which of course is a
cardiovascular nightmare if
overabundant. So we see that the gene
expression for P AI1 is increased when a
stimulant like LPS is applied to the
endothelial cells but the effect is
supercharged given a drug that blocks
CPT1. Fun fact, I've actually used this
drug in the lab before for the exact
same reason. So again without access to
fat metabolism these cells experienced
increased clotting signatures in
conjunction with increased cell stress.
Similar data is seen when looking at
inflammation specifically immune cells
like lucasytes. So fat metabolism is
continuously shown to be important for
keeping cells in their quiescent state
but also keeping them from encouraging a
pro-inflammatory pro clotting state. Now
that we understand all that, what can be
done about it all? Well, there's a
potent solution that the researchers
uncover, which I'm excited to show you,
as well as how to implement. However,
before that, there's something else that
the endothelial cells do called cellular
compensation along with a fascinating
signaling cascade within the cells
called notch signaling along with ways
of improving CPT1, that influential
protein sitting on the mitochondrial
membrane for fat metabolism and even
some specifics getting into the
solutions. All of that, a ton of cell
biology and applicable information is
part of the extended version of the
video that you're currently watching,
included for the Physionic Insiders.
That doesn't even mention all the perks
like a private podcast, vast library of
exclusive videos and articles, protocols
and guides, live sessions with me, and
more. Check it out. I put a lot of work
into it and the insider community is
really great. Link is in the
description. So, what is the solution
here? How do we protect our endothelial
cells and protect our arteries by
keeping them quiescent? The answer is
here. Here we're measuring those
reactive oxygen species. So the lower
the bar, the better. We have the CPT1
knockdown like before. We have the
stressor applied to the cells. So LPS
and we have dare I say a solution
acetate, a short chain fat. We again see
a lack of fat metabolism assumed.
Increases reactive oxygen species.
That's not news to us veterans. However,
when adding acetate, that increased
level drops back down. But how is
acetate a fat molecule doing that if
CPT1 is still knocked down? Remember,
for fats to enter the mitochondria, they
have to engage with CPT-1 and acetate is
a short-chain fat. Well, that's because
short-chain fats can diffuse across the
mitochondrial membrane without the need
for CPT1. That is not the case for most
other fats as we've described. So either
you can bypass CPT1 through a short
chain fat like acetate or you can
improve CPT1's function which I'll get
into in the extended version of this
video. Now similarly measures of immune
cells identified by the proteins on the
cell surface like CD45 are also reduced
with acetate administration. Now we have
multiple measures that indicate acetate
can help quiet and the tumult inside the
endothelial cells. But that leaves us
with a final question. Where do we get
acetate? Now granted, all these data are
in cells and some in animals, but many
of the experiments are in human cells.
And there's long-term data that sources
of acetate that we're about to get into
that show effects at improving
cardiovascular health. So while this is
quite mechanism focused, we have some
clinical data indicating benefit. So our
body produces acetate, but we can
increase it. For one, metabolizing
alcohol in your liver leads to acetate,
but let's not pretend like pounding
beers is suddenly going to help your
cardiovascular system. The major source
is from your intestinal microbiome, the
bacteria, the viruses, and so forth in
your intestines. As a result, we can
increase your acetate production and
absorption by simply eating more of
vinegar-based foods like pickled
vegetables, fermented tea. And another
big one is dietary fiber sources like
legumes, artichokes, leaks, whole
grains, and anything of that ilk. These
resistant fibers are taken up by
bacteria and converted to acetate which
is then absorbed by your colonocytes in
the intestinal wall which pours them
into the bloodstream. And guess what's
waiting there to suck that acetate into
their receptive mitochondria.
That's right, your endothelial cells. So
all that to explain an incredibly
dynamic nature of your endothelial cell
health through metabolism. Stressed
endothelial cells tend to be linked to
glycolysis of glucose metabolism and
healthier quiescent cells rely on fat
metabolism. You can support that fat
metabolism through consuming acidate
encouraging foods like vinegar-based
foods, fermented foods, and dietary
fibers. Speaking to that last one, I
actually go over more on fibers and
their impact on your health. Allow me to
fascinate you right here, too. I'll
speak with you over there. Thanks for
tuning in.